A tone generator, also known as a toner probe,
traces a copper cable wire in a wall.
This tool is a two-piece tool in which a tone
generator is connected to one end of a cable
connection, and then a toner probe is connected
to the other end.
A tone is generated when a connection is made.
If there is no tone, chances are there is
a problem with the cable.
Tone generators are also used to find out
which cable is terminated in which spot in
a 110 block, which is a necessary task if
the cables are not properly labeled in the
first place.
This particular process, as you can imagine,
can be rather laborious.
One time, I needed to use this tool to figure
out which of five dangling cables from a ceiling
was connected to a server in another room.
I had the probe in one hand and a cell phone
in the other with a coworker that let me know
when a tone was generated.
Wouldn't you know it?
I forgot the labeler, so I had to run down,
get that, and verify this again.
It pays to plan when troubleshooting.